This picture
هذه الصورة
is from my metro card
هي من بطاقة المترو الخاصة بي
when I spent a year abroad in Paris in college in the mid-'90s.
عندما قضيت عاما في الخارج في (باريس) بالجامعة في منتصف التسعينات.
My friend says I look like a French anarchist --
يقول صديقي أنني أبدو كفوضوي فرنسي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But this is still what I see
لكن هذا لايزال ما أراه
when I look in the mirror in the morning.
عندما أنظر إلى المرآة في الصباح.
Within a month of living in Paris, I'd lost 15 pounds
خلال شهر من الحياة في (باريس)، خسرت 15 رطلاً
and I was in the best shape of my life
وكنت في أفضل حالاتي على الإطلاق
because I was eating fresh food
لأني كنت أتناول طعاما طازجا
and I was walking wherever I went.
وكنت أذهب مشيا إلى كل مكان.
Having grown up in suburban Atlanta,
كوني ترعرت في ضواحي (أتلانتا)،
a region built largely by highways and automobiles
منطقة مبنية إلى حد كبير من الطرق السريعة والسيارات
and with a reputation as a poster child for sprawl,
وبسُمعة كطفل مدلل للتمدد،
Paris fundamentally changed the way I understood
(باريس) غيرت بشكل جذري طريقة فهمي
the construction of the world around me,
لتركيبة العالم من حولي،
and I got obsessed with the role of infrastructure --
وأصبحت مهووسا بدور البنية التحتية
that it's not just the way to move people from point A to point B,
أنها ليست مجرد وسيلة لتحريك الناس من نقطة (أ) إلى نقطة (ب)،
it's not just the way to convey water or sewage or energy,
أنها ليست مجرد وسيلة لنقل المياه أو المجاري أو الطاقة،
but it's the foundation for our economy.
ولكنها الأساس لإقتصادنا.
It's the foundation for our social life and for our culture,
إنها الأساس لحياتنا الإجتماعية ولثقافتنا،
and it really matters to the way that we live.
وهي مهمة جدا لأسلوب حياتنا.
When I came home, I was instantly frustrated,
عندما عدت إلى الوطن، أُصبت بالإحباط فورا،
stuck in traffic as I crossed the top end of our perimeter highway.
عالق في زحمة المرور بينما أعبر الجهة العليا من محيط طريقنا السريع.
Not only was I not moving a muscle,
لم أكن عاجزا عن الحركة تماما فحسب،
I had no social interaction
بل لم يكن لدي أي تواصل اجتماعي
with the hundreds of thousands of people that were hurtling past me,
مع مئات الآلاف من الأشخاص الذين كانوا يمرَون مسرعين من حولي،
like me, with their eyes faced forward and their music blaring.
مثلي، كانت أعينهم متوجهة إلى الأمام وموسيقاهم صاخبة.
I wondered if this was an inevitable outcome,
تساءلت لو كانت هذه نتيجة محتومة،
or could we do something about it.
أو هل يمكننا عمل شيء ما بشأنها.
Was it possible to transform this condition in Atlanta
هل من الممكن أن يتحوَل هذا الوضع في (أتلانتا)
into the kind of place that I wanted to live in?
إلى نوعية المكان الذي كنت أرغب في العيش فيه؟
I went back to grad school in architecture and city planning,
عدت إلى الدراسة في تخصص الهندسة المعمارية وتخطيط المدن،
developed this interest in infrastructure,
وتطور لدي هذا الإهتمام بالبنى التحتية،
and in 1999 came up with an idea
وفي عام 1999 خطرت لي فكرة
for my thesis project:
لمشروع أطروحتي:
the adaptation of an obsolete loop of old railroad circling downtown
استخدام حلقة مهملة من السكة الحديدية القديمة المحيطة بوسط المدينة
as a new infrastructure for urban revitalization.
كبنية تحتية جديدة لإنعاش المدينة.
It was just an idea.
كانت مجرَد فكرة.
I never thought we would actually build it.
لم أظن أبدا أننا سنطبقها فعلا.
But I went to work at an architecture firm,
لكنني عدت إلى العمل في شركة للهندسة المعمارية،
and eventually talked to my coworkers about it,
وتحدثت مع زملائي عنها،
and they loved the idea.
وأحبوا الفكرة.
And as we started talking to more people about it,
وبينما بدأنا بالحديث عن الفكرة مع أشخاص أكثر،
more people wanted to hear about it.
كان المزيد منهم يرغبون بالسماع عنها.
In the summer of 2001,
في صيف عام 2001،
we connected with Cathy Woolard,
تواصلنا مع (كاثي وولارد)،
who was soon elected city council president.
التي انتخبت بعدها رئيسة لمجلس المدينة.
And we built a citywide vision around this idea:
وقمنا ببناء رؤية شاملة للمدينة حول هذه الفكرة:
the Atlanta BeltLine, a 22-mile loop
"أتلانتا بيلت لاين"، حلقة من السكك بطول 22 ميلا
of transit and trails and transformation.
من النقل والمسارات والتحوَل.
I was doing two and three meetings a week for two and a half years,
كنت أحضر إجتماعين إلى ثلاثة إجتماعات في الأسبوع لمدة سنتين ونصف،
and so was Cathy and her staff and a handful of volunteers.
وكذلك (كاثي) والموظفين لديها ومجموعة من المتطوعين.
Together, we built this amazing movement of people and ideas.
معاً، قمنا ببناء هذه الحركة المدهشة من الأشخاص والأفكار.
It included community advocates who were used to fighting against things,
تضمنت المدافعين عن المجتمع الذين اعتادوا محاربة الأشياء،
but found the Atlanta BeltLine as something that they could fight for;
لكن وجدوا "أتلانتا بيلت لاين" أمرا يمكن ان يحاربوا من أجله؛
developers who saw the opportunity
المطورون الذين وجدوا الفرصة
to take advantage of a lot of new growth in the city;
للإستفادة من حركة التنمية الكبيرة في المدينة.
and dozens of nonprofit partners who saw their mission
والعديد من الشركاء الغير ربحيين الذين رأوا أن مهمتهم
at least partly accomplished by the shared vision.
تتحقق جزئيا على الأقل من خلال الرؤية المشتركة.
Now, usually these groups of people aren't at the same table
الأن، عادة لاتجتمع هذه المجموعات من الناس على الطاولة نفسها
wanting the same outcome.
راغبين في تحقيق النتيجة ذاتها.
But there we were, and it was kind of weird,
ولكن ها نحن ذا، وكان الأمرغريبا نوعا ما،
but it was really, really powerful.
لكنه كان قويا جدا حقا.
The people of Atlanta fell in love with a vision
سكان (أتلانتا) وقعوا في حب الرؤية
that was better than what they saw through their car windshields,
التي كانت أفضل مما كانوا يرونه عبر زجاج سياراتهم،
and the people of Atlanta made it happen,
وسكان (أتلانتا) جعلوها حقيقة،
and I guarantee you we would not be building it otherwise.
وأؤكد لكم أننا لم نكن لنبنيها لو لم يفعلوا ذلك.
From the beginning, our coalition was diverse.
منذ البداية كان تحالفنا متنوعاً.
People of all stripes were part of our story.
أُناس من جميع الأنواع كانوا جزءا من قصتنا.
People on the lower end of the economic spectrum loved it, too.
الأشخاص من الحد الأدنى من السلم الإقتصادي أحبوا الأمر أيضا.
They were just afraid they weren't going to be able to be there
كانوا خائفين فقط من عدم قدرتهم على التواجد
when it got built, that they'd be priced out.
عندما تُبنى، بأن لا يتمكنوا من تحمَل التكلفة.
And we've all heard that kind of story before, right?
وقد سمعنا جميعا هذا النوع من القصص من قبل، أليس كذلك؟
But we promised that the Atlanta BeltLine would be different,
لكننا وعدنا بأن "أتلانتا بيلت لاين" ستكون مختلفة،
and people took ownership of the idea,
وآمن الناس بالفكرة،
and they made it better than anything we ever imagined
وجعلوها أفضل من أي شيء تخيلناه على الإطلاق
in the beginning,
في البداية،
including significant subsidies for housing,
من ضمن ذلك إعانات كبيرة للسكن،
new parks, art, an arboretum -- a list that continues to grow.
حدائق جديدة، فنون، أماكن للتشجير، وتستمر القائمة في الإمتداد.
And we put in place
وقمنا نحن بتأسيس
the organizations and agencies that were required to make it happen.
المنظمات والمؤسسات التي كانت مُلزمة بتحقيق ذلك.
And importantly, it is.
والأهم أنها تفعل ذلك.
Now we're in the early stages of implementation, and it's working.
الأن نحن في المراحل الأولى من التطبيق، والأمور تعمل على ما يرام.
The first mainline section of trail was opened in 2012,
اُفتتح القسم الأول من الخط الرئيسي للطرق عام 2012،
and it's already generated over three billion dollars
وأنتج منذ ذلك الحين أكثر من ثلاثة مليار دولار
of private-sector investment.
من استثمارات القطاع الخاص.
But it's not only changing the physical form of the city,
ولكنه لا يغير الشكل المادي فقط للمدينة،
it's changing the way we think about the city,
إنه يغير الطريقة التي نفكر فيها عن المدينة،
and what our expectations are for living there.
وماهي توقعاتنا للحياة هناك.
About a month ago,
منذ حوالي شهر،
I had to take my kids with me to the grocery store
اضطررت لإصطحاب أطفالي إلى متجر البقالة
and they were complaining about it,
وكانوا يتذّمرون بشان ذلك،
because they didn't want to get in the car.
لأنهم لم يرغبوا بركوب السيارة.
They were saying, "Dad, if we have to go,
كانوا يقولون، "أبي، إن كان لابد لنا من الذهاب،
can we at least ride our bikes?"
هل يكننا على الأقل ركوب دراجاتنا؟"
And I said, "Of course we can.
وقلت أنا، "بالتأكيد يمكنكم ذلك.
That's what people in Atlanta do.
هذا ما يفعله الناس في (أتلانتا).
We ride our bikes to the grocery store."
نحن نركب دراجاتنا إلى متجر البقالة."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you, yeah.
شكرا لكم، نعم.
Now, they don't know how ridiculous that is,
الأن، هم لا يعرفون كم هو سخيف فعل ذلك،
but I do.
لكنني أعرف.
And I also understand that their expectations for Atlanta
وأنا أيضا أفهم أن توقعاتهم ل(أتلانتا)
are really powerful.
قوية بحق.
This kind of transformation is exactly like sprawl
هذا النوع من التحوَل هو بالضبط كالتمدد
in the last century,
خلال القرن الأخير.
the movement where our investment in highways and automobiles
الحركة التي تسببت فيها استثماراتنا في االطرق السريعة و السيارات
fundamentally changed American life.
بتغيير الحياة الأمريكية بشكل جذري.
That wasn't some grand conspiracy.
لم تكن تلك مؤامرة كبرى من نوع ما.
There were conspiracies within it, of course.
كان هناك مؤامرات داخلها بالطبع.
But it was a cultural momentum.
لكنها كانت زخماً ثقافياً.
It was millions of people making millions of decisions
كان الملايين من الأشخاص يتخذون الملايين من القرارات
over an extended period of time,
على مدى فترة ممتدة من الزمن،
that fundamentally changed not only the way that we build cities,
والتي لم تغيَر بشكل أساسي الطريقة التي نبني بها المدن فحسب،
but it changed our expectations
وإنما غيرت توقعاتنا
for our lives.
لحياتنا.
These changes were the foundations for urban sprawl.
هذه التغييرات كانت الأساس للزحف العمراني.
We didn't call it sprawl at that time.
لم نكن نطلق عليها "الزحف" في ذلك الوقت.
We called it the future.
كنا نطلق عليها "المستقبل".
And it was.
وكانت كذلك.
And we got all the highways and strip malls and cul-de-sacs we wanted.
وحصلنا على كل الطرق السريعة ومجمعات التسوق الصغيرة والأزقة المغلقة التي أردناها.
It was a radical transformation,
كان تحولاً جذرياً،
but it was built by a cultural momentum.
لكنه بُني عن طريق الزخم الثقافي.
So it's important to not separate
لذلك من المهم أن لا نفصل
the physical construction of the places we live
البناء المادي للأماكن التي نعيش فيها
from other things that are happening at that time.
عن الأمور الأخرى التي تحدث في الوقت ذاته.
At that time,
في ذلك الوقت،
in the second half of the last century,
في النصف الثاني من القرن الماضي،
science was curing disease
كان العلم يعالج الأمراض
and lifting us to the moon,
ويرفعنا إلى القمر،
and the sexual revolution was breaking down barriers,
وكانت الثورة الجنسية تحطَم الحواجز،
and the Civil Rights Movement began its march
وبدأت "حركة الحقوق المدنية" مسيرتها
toward the fulfillment of our nation's promise.
نحو تحقيق وعود أمتنا.
Television, entertainment, food, travel, business -- everything was changing,
التلفزيون، التسلية، الطعام، السفر المشاريع التجارية -- كل شيء كان يتغير،
and both the public and private sectors were colluding
وكلا القطاعين العام والخاص كانا يعملان سوية
to give us the lives we wanted.
لمنحنا الحياة التي نريدها.
The Federal Highway Administration,
الإدارة الفيدرالية للطرق السريعة،
for example, didn't exist before there were highways.
على سبيل المثال، لم تُوجد قبل أن يكون هناك طرق سريعة.
Think about it.
فكروا في الأمر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Of course, today it's important to understand and acknowledge
بالطبع، من المهم اليوم أن نفهم ونعترف
that those benefits accrued to some groups of people
بأن تلك المنافع حصلت لبعض المجموعات من الناس
and not to others.
ولم تحصل للبعض الآخر.
It was not an equitable cultural momentum.
لم يكن زخما ثقافيا منصفا.
But when we look today in wonder and disgust, maybe,
ولكن عندما ننظر اليوم بتساؤل وتقزز، ربما،
at the metropolis sprawl before us,
إلى إمتداد المدينة أمامنا،
we wonder if we're stuck.
نتساءل إن كنا عالقين.
Are we stuck with the legacy of that inequity?
هل نحن عالقون مع إرث ذلك الظلم؟
Are we stuck with this dystopian traffic hellscape?
هل نحن عالقون مع جحيم المرور البائس هذا؟
Are we stuck with rampant urban displacement,
هل نحن عالقون مع نزوح المناطق الحضرية المتفشي،
with environmental degradation?
مع التدهور البيئي؟
Are we stuck with social isolation
هل نحن عالقون مع العزل الإجتماعي
or political polarization?
أو الإستقطاب السياسي؟
Are these the inevitable and permanent outcomes?
هل هذه هي المخرجات الدائمة والتي لابد منها؟
Or are they the result of our collective cultural decisions
أم هل هي نتائج قراراتنا الثقافية الجمعية
that we've made for ourselves?
التي صنعناها لأنفسنا؟
And if they are,
وإن كانت كذلك،
can't we change them?
ألا يمكننا أن نغيرها؟
What I have learned from our experience in Atlanta
ما تعلمته من تجربتنا في (أتلانتا)
is not an anomaly.
ليس أمرا استثنائيا.
Similar stories are playing out everywhere,
قصص مشابهة تحدث في كل مكان،
where people are reclaiming not only old railroads,
حيث الناس لا يطالبون باستعادة السكك الحديدية القديمة فقط،
but also degraded urban waterways and obsolete roadways,
ولكن المجاري الممرات المائية الحضرية المتضررة والطرق المُهملة،
reinventing all of the infrastructure
ليعيدوا تجديد كل البنى التحتية
in their lives.
في حياتهم.
Whether here in New York
سواء هنا في (نيويورك)
or in Houston
أو في (هيوستن)
or Miami,
أو (ميامي)
Detroit, Philadelphia,
(ديترويت)، (فيلادلفيا)،
Seoul, Hong Kong, Singapore,
(سيول)، (هونج كونج)، (سنغافورة)،
Toronto and Paris,
(تورنتو) و (باريس)،
cities big and small all over the world are reclaiming and reinventing
مدن كبيرة وصغيرة حول العالم تقوم بإستعادة وتجديد
this infrastructure for themselves,
هذه البنية التحتية لأنفسهم،
including the mother of all catalyst infrastructure projects,
من ضمنها المشروع الأم لجميع مشاريع البنى التحتية المحفزَة،
the Los Angeles River,
مشروع "نهر (لوس أنجليس)"،
the revitalization effort for which similarly started
مجهود تنشيطي بدء بشكل مماثل
as a grassroots movement,
كحركة شعبية بيئية،
has developed into a cultural momentum,
تطوَر إلى زخم ثقافي،
and is now in the early stages of being transformed
والأن هو في مراحله الأولى من التحوَل
into some kind of life-affirming infrastructure again,
إلى نوع من البنية التحتية الداعمة للحياة من جديد،
this one with trails and parks and fishing and boating
وهذه المرة مع طرق وحدائق وصيد وركوب زوارق
and community revitalization,
وإنعاش للمجتمع،
and of course, water quality and flood control.
وبالطبع، جودة المياه و السيطرة على الفيضانات.
It's already improving the lives of people.
وقد بدأت تحسَن من حياة الناس فعليا.
It's already changing the way the rest of us think about Los Angeles.
إنها تغير فعليا الطريقة التي يفكر بها بقيتنا عن (لوس أنجليس).
This is more than just infrastructure.
هذه أكثر من مجرد بنية تحتية.
We're building new lives for ourselves.
نحن نبني حياة جديدة لأنفسنا.
It's a movement that includes local food, urban agriculture,
إنها حركة تشمل الأطعمة المحليَة والزراعة الحضرية،
craft beer, the maker movement,
البيرة الحرفية وحركة الصناعة المستقلة،
tech and design -- all of these things, early indicators of a really radical shift
التكنولوجيا والتصميم، وكل هذه الأمور هي مؤشرات مبكَرة لتحوَل جذري حقا
in the way we build cities.
في الطريقة التي نبني بها المدن.
We're taking places like this
نحن نأخذ أماكن كهذه
and transforming them into this.
ونحوَلها إلى هذه.
And soon this.
وقريبا إلى هذه.
And this is all exciting and good.
وكل هذا مثير وجيد.
We're changing the world for the better.
نحن نغير العالم إلى الأفضل.
Good for us!
هذا جيَد لنا!
And it is awesome -- I mean that.
وهو أمر رائع، وأعني ذلك.
But our history of sprawl,
ولكن تاريخنا في الإمتداد،
and from what we can already see with these catalyst projects today,
وممَا يمكن رؤيته مسبقا مع المشروعات التحفيزية اليوم،
we know and must remember
نحن نعلم ويجب أن نتذكر
that big changes like this don't usually benefit everyone.
أن التغييرات الكبيرة مثل هذه لا تكون مفيدة للجميع في العادة.
The market forces unleashed by this cultural momentum
القوى التجارية التي تم إطلاقها عن طريق هذا الزخم الثقافي
often include the seemingly unstoppable
عادة ما تشمل ما لا يمكن منعه كما يبدو
and inevitable cycle of rising taxes, prices and rents.
من إرتفاع محتوم في الضرائب والأسعار والإيجارات.
This is urgent.
هذه مشكلة طارئة.
If we care, we have to stand up
إن كنَا نهتم، يجب علينا ان نقف
and speak out.
ونتكلم عنها.
This should be a call to action,
يجب أن تكون هذه دعوة للتحرك،
because the answer can't be to not improve communities.
لأن الإجابة لا يمكن أن تكون هي عدم تطوير المجتمعات.
The answer can't be to not build parks and transit and grocery stores.
الإجابة لا يمكن أن تكون هي عدم إنشاء الحدائق وطرق المواصلات ومتاجر البقالة.
The answer can't be to hold communities down
الإجابة لا يمكن أن تكون هي تعطيل المجتمعات
just to keep them affordable.
فقط للمحافظة على انخفاض الأسعار.
But we do have to follow through and address the financial realities
ولكن يجب أن نتابع الأمر ونتعامل مع الحقائق الإقتصادية
that we're facing.
التي نواجهها.
This is hard, and it won't happen on its own.
إنه أمر صعب، ولن يحقق نفسه بنفسه.
We can do it, and I'm committed to this goal in Atlanta,
نحن نستطيع القيام به، وأنا ملتزم بهذا الهدف في (أتلانتا)،
to sticking up again for people who made it possible in the first place.
للوقوف مرة أخرى بجانب الأشخاص الذين جعلوا هذا الأمر ممكنا من الأساس.
We can't call it a success without them.
لا يمكننا أن نسمَيه نجاحا بدونهم.
I certainly can't,
أنا لا يمكنني ذلك بالتأكيد.
because the people I made commitments to all those years
لأن الأشخاص الذين التزمت معهم كل هذه السنوات
weren't abstract populations.
لم يكونوا مجتمعات مبهمة.
They're my friends and neighbors.
إنهم أصدقائي وجيراني.
They're people that I love.
إنهم أُناس أحبهم.
So even though it started as my graduate thesis
ولذلك برغم أن الأمر بدء كأطروحة تخرجي
and I'm working hard for 16 years with thousands of people
وأنا أعمل بجدَ منذ 16 عاما مع الألاف من الأشخاص
to help make this thing come to life,
لأساعد في تحقيق هذا الأمر على أرض الواقع،
I know and believe that who the BeltLine is being built for
أعرف وأؤمن أن من يتم بناء (بيلت لاين) من أجلهم
is just as important as whether it's built at all.
هم في مثل أهمية إنشاءه.
Not just in Atlanta,
ليس فقط في (أتلانتا)،
but locally and globally,
ولكن محليا وعالميا،
we have to understand
يجب أن نفهم
this accountability to the people whose lives we are changing,
هذه المسؤولية تجاه البشر الذين تتغير حياتهم،
because this is us.
لأن هؤلاء هم نحن.
We are the lives we're talking about.
نحن الحياة التي نتحدث عنها.
These places aren't inevitable.
هذه الأماكن ليست محتومة.
The places we live aren't inevitable,
الأماكن التي نعيش فيها ليست محتومة،
and if we want something different, we just need to speak up.
وإن أردنا شيئا مختلفا، فعلينا فقط أن نوصل أصواتنا.
We have to ensure that change comes on our terms.
يجب أن نتأكد من أن يحدث التغيير بشروطنا.
And to do that,
ولنقوم بذلك،
we have to participate actively in the process of shaping change.
لا بد من أن نشارك بفعالية في عملية صياغة التغيير.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)